<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<dublin_core schema="dc"><dcvalue element="publisher">Applied Physiology, Nutrition, and Metabolism</dcvalue><dcvalue element="publication" qualifier="journal">Applied Physiology, Nutrition, and Metabolism</dcvalue><dcvalue element="identifier" qualifier="issn">1715-5312 </dcvalue><dcvalue element="title">Associations between dairy intake and metabolic risk parameters in a healthy French-Canadian population</dcvalue><dcvalue element="contributor" qualifier="author">Da Silva, Marine S.</dcvalue><dcvalue element="affiliation" qualifier="institution">CHU de Québec Research Center</dcvalue><dcvalue element="type">Article</dcvalue><dcvalue element="identifier" qualifier="doi">10.1139/apnm-2014-0154</dcvalue><dcvalue element="date" qualifier="submitted">2014-04-28</dcvalue><dcvalue element="date" qualifier="revised">2014-07-02</dcvalue><dcvalue element="date" qualifier="available">2014-07-07</dcvalue><dcvalue element="description" qualifier="abstract">Background: Observational studies support that dairy product intake is associated with a reduced risk of developing type 2 diabetes; however, several clinical studies report conflicting results on the association between dairy product consumption and metabolic parameters. The aim of this study was to determine associations between dairy product consumption and metabolic profile. Methods: Dietary data, using a validated food frequency questionnaire, and fasting blood samples were collected from 233 French-Canadians. Plasma phospholipid (PL) fatty acids (FA) concentrations were determined by gas chromatography. Results: Subjects consumed 2.5±1.4 portions of dairy products daily, including 1.6±1.3 portions of low-fat (LF) and 0.90±0.70 portions of high-fat (HF) dairy products. Trans-palmitoleic acid level in plasma PL was related to HF dairy consumption (r=0.15; p=0.04). Total (r=−0.21; p=0.001) and LF dairy (r=−0.20; p=0.003) intakes were inversely correlated with fasting plasma glucose level. Total dairy intake was inversely associated to systolic blood pressure (SBP) (r=−0.17; p=0.008) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) (r=−0.14; p=0.03). LF dairy intake was also inversely correlated with SBP (r=−0.17; p=0.009). Total dairy intake was correlated with plasma C-reactive protein (CRP) (r=0.15; p=0.03). No association was found between HF dairy consumption and the risk factors studied. Conclusion: Dairy intake is inversely associated with glycaemia and BP; yet, it may modify CRP levels. Moreover, trans-palmitoleic FA levels in plasma PL may be potentially used to assess full-fat dairy consumption.</dcvalue></dublin_core>